this one if you can speak about death
death contemplation how should we think
about this and this is a very sore
bacteria from a terracotta verse 6.13
vice sity Monda cigarette butt the
section I'll read read the whole thing
the world is beaten down by death and
surrounded by old age a dart of craving
has laid it low and it's always fuming
designer the world is beaten down by
death encircled surrounded by old age
beaten constantly without respite like a
thief being flogged three things are
coming like a wall of flame death
disease and old age no power can stand
before them and those speeds enough to
flee don't waste your day a little or a lot
don't waste your day a little or a lot
every night that passes shortens your
life by that much walking or standing or
sitting or lying down your final night
draws near you have no time to be cares
so walking and standing sitting or
laying down you should be dwelling on
the ultimate context which is what death
is it's an ultimate context to your life
it's a non-negotiable context because
people might think oh I must be going
through the motions and methods of
practicing mindfulness of death thinking
about thinking about it when I'm walking
when I'm sitting that's true only in a
sense that you need to discern the the
most fundamental over always present
possibility of death which is why makes
it such an ultimate context of your life
everything else within your life hmm can
come and go that has been could have not
been all these things but one thing for
sure when life is there death is its
guarantee as they are as though as the
final outcome of it so under reason why
people would be pressed and oppressed by
their desires by their intentions and
skillful actions is because you turn a
blind eye to this very factual liability
to death so death possibility of death
is certain death is possible in a way of
what is possible is you might die this
way or that way but possibility of death
is certain as an outcome and so if a
person would not be turning a blind eye
to it that's all it is something that's
gonna start shaping your life
differently because many pretty much
everything unwholesome that a person can
engage with that you can engage with is
is an account of ignoring the fact that
you will die ignoring the fact that you
will not always be healthy not always be
young being intoxicated by those
things and that's how you entertain
desire you more more of it but all you
need to do is uncover that fundamental
context of well certainty of death and
it will already prevent you
automatically prevent you from how far
you will be able to proliferate down the
rabbit hole of desires and so on and
that's that's that's what mindfulness of
death means obviously you can do that in
a very loose level but you can start
narrowing it down and you realize it you
might not see the end of this day not
not necessarily you must have to like
become neurotic about it others die I
will die just know recognize that
possibility is so immediate that you
might not see the end of the day you
might not see the other in the morning
you are not have enough time to finish
your meal you are not have enough time
to breathe out once you breathe in its
that how much you're not in control of
your life fundamentally that doesn't
mean that you should be trying to like
you should be repeating to yourself that
you will die every second of your day
that's not contemplation of death
there's just mechanical repetition of
the idea of what that is for you now you
want to understand the context of death
which is that ultimate peripheral
context to everything you actually do in
your life so the hands the mind front
whatever there is a principle of
peripheral there's a principle of
mindfulness peripheral awareness so by
being mindful of the context of death in
regard to day-to-day life that's already
mindfulness practice of mindfulness so
if a person wants to start practicing
that contemplation of death as
meditation yeah as we any other
meditation withdraw yourself from
distractions from company and yeah think
about I think like if you don't know
where to start just think about the
nature of death that is inescapable to
you it's just it's gonna come and you can
it's just it's gonna come and you can
which then you think that furthers our
thinking okay so what is what would be
the real significance then of this life
there is fully within that control of
death because whatever you do in this
life cannot make you step outside of the
liability to death it cannot basically
free you from death so then you start up
when you realize the dead order cannot
change doesn't matter what you do
doesn't matter what you distract
yourself with doesn't matter what you
accomplish with this life fundamentally
that whole thing as much as you
developed it as far as it proliferated
it's still equally within the domain of
death and you can't escape that
so the practice them would be
establishing that right order that
doesn't matter what you do in this life
fundamentally you're liable to sickness
aging and death context is not something
you need to keep in front of you and
think about I'll die I will die no just
keep you to the back of your mind where
it is Oh while I'm doing this this is
this I might die it's highly likely I'll
die as a result of you know sitting in
my room reading a book but death is
equally present there because my life
depends upon working organs upon beating
heart breathing lungs so if you want to
practice mindfulness of death you see
that your life is undermined by by the
random operation of organs that you have
no control over what about the example
of you're on coal you have a job you can
be called to work at any point you will
be cool cuz that you do tourism that job
mm-hmm so whatever you do has to be done
with that in the back of your mind
yeah some of the quarries well that's
what I mean by context exactly so but
it's not just it's not that sort of
context you can be indifferent to
because it's the context that undermines
and affects your life yeah so yeah and
okay there's the similar that would be
for example the like say you have what
about oh yeah like a job interview you
have one shot that's something that can
change your life
in a week's time whatever you do for
them week this would be the back of your
mind because it is so important and you
will be exactly there is a degree of
concern in regard to it now imagine if
that one shot it's basically death it's
not like a random interview that can go
either way it's it's it's as fundamental
as losing your life so you realize what
kind of concern would that be
peripherally and how much influence
would that have on your choices and
decisions in this life and hence the
Dhammapada verse like it was about the
anger wasn't it
beginning but it said how do you go well
it does yeah
those who quarrel they forget that we
are all gonna die
they see they were all sentenced to
death in this life and because of that
quarrels persist and quarrels develop
because if you don't forget the ultimate
appointment with death that you have
that can and also again you can't have a
like you know you can have a job
appointment exactly the exact time exact
day but appointment with death isn't
uncertain in the sense that it can arise
at any given time so you realize that
appointment might be today might be
tomorrow might be in ten years time I
can't forget about it
I cannot forget about it because it can
be here the next moment because if I
forget about it I might fail so whatever
you do that in this life you do it on
the basis of not forgetting about the
ultimate context of your liability to
die certain possibility of death and
that already you could see how much less
you would be able to be pulled by the
fleeting desires those sensors or
distractions and so on you just you just
will not make and it would not have any
value and again if you ever if a person
has any doubt about it just to recollect
when you feared for your life for a
period of time on account of anything
the illness or accident or whatever and
seeing how much interest you had in the
world during that period of time you see
very little you were not enjoying your
food you are not finding solace in
friends and distraction and parties or
whatever else it was just this was the
most pressing thing so it's basically
reconnecting to that context that is
there so you don't have to fabricate it
you just have to stop covering it up
with that constant like influx of
sensuality and the intentions for
distraction so if you always feel like
you're on call then you might be called
upon by death
that's already means you already
developed fundamentally that proper
context which now shapes your decisions
makes you non careless in regard to
things in front of you in your life and
that's essentially what mindfulness of
death is mindfulness of the certain Oh
today I have to do this safe to work in
the garden and I have to go dance they
have to go supermarket or or and you all
these things can stay but you would see
how much less emotionally will be pulled
or affected by any of those things
whether they change whether they the way
you wanted to be or they go the other
way you wouldn't be affected why because you
you wouldn't be affected why because you
were not there with them why because
your concern about death but that kind
of practice can be a bit too sharp for
some people that concern can overwhelm
you but if it doesn't you could see how
quickly you will develop this passion in
regard to everything that comes your way
and that's really Buddha praised it's
pretty much the quickest way to free
your mind from any unwholesome state and
ignorance and avoidance of
responsibility and so on but if it's too
much then you practice mindfulness of
breathing cuz it results in the same as
we spoke in the other talks you realize
that you fully controlled active
breathing depends on things that are not
your own while you're controlling it
which means your own sense of control is
undermined by fundamental depending upon
things you cannot control I don't go for
it today first you imagine mentioning
I don't party what's in there Terra Gaza
others don't understand that our lives
must have limits our lives have limits
those who do understand this settle then
quarrels right away yeah yeah you're
saying it's the most important thing to
your life is the fact that you have an
appointment so if you like then you can
also use that in the reverse order and
you can see if you think oh boy I am
practicing mindfulness of death I'm
making the effort
okay is what I getting angry am I
getting last for you the answer is yes
means you you have an established
context of death because if you were you
would know these things would not be
able to arise let alone possessed you
will be doing trivial things okay
founded by impossible inconceivable
inconceivable the only time the only way
you can be triggered by trivial matters
or non trivial matters the only way you
could be emotionally triggered by
anything is if you have lost the context
of certain death that's you and yours
only then literally nothing else matters
because everything is within that
context everything there's nothing you
can do say you're think they will not be
within the context of life that's
undermined by death just you know so the
practice of mindfulness of death as I
said it's not a mechanical repetition of
certain thoughts I will die trying to
keep it in front of you not forget about
it it's really just clarifying the
understanding of that inherent context
in whatever you do the context of that
ultimate final cessation that that you
cannot even conceive escaping from
because when you think about escaping
from the thoughts of that escape are
within the context of death so you're
fully enclosed by so that's why it can
be quite frightening like being buried
alive for example you're still alive but
you realize the escape from this is
inconceivable and that's the simile the
Buddha gave to that king when you said
what if I tell you there is a big
mountain coming to crush you from an
army an army coming from the east
West what if it's coming from the West
I'll go nobody's come from West North
and East I'll go south well it come from
all four directions like mountings and
closing you and you can't escape you
can't fight against it what would you do
then oh well then I will reevaluate my
life and maybe become a monk and try and
free myself internally cuz yeah that's
what life is there is no escape in any
direction from that liability to death
and it's on the basis of simple ignoring
fact obvious truth not letting it sink
in that's what people get up to also to
unwholesome horrible things as well
people can do just in the kind of well
pretty much if you do that you don't
have to worry about most of the other
things that you worry about yeah so you
replace which is better
thousands of what is that overwhelm you
every single day or just develop one
fundamental concern whereby everything
else is included and nothing can affect
you on account of it that's a good deal
but not for the mind that's not trained
not for the mind it hasn't developed
virtue they can't see that as a good
deal they just see that as a direct
threat and terror why because they still
have a view that sensuality distraction
actor will will any anything any any
little things that you do based on
passion they still value that as a mean
of escape they imply that if I don't
think about death I'm not affected by it
that's not like a rational thought that
a pre-planned now simply the habit of
ignoring maintains that ignorance so you
feel like you're sheltered from death
until of course circumstances remind you
that it's otherwise until you have
little pangs of anxiety that then you
can't get rid of for the rest of your
life why cuz you never admit yourself
what's obvious right from the start that
it as soon as you're born you're old
enough to die pretty much the second you
come come you conceived
you're liable to death and that's it
so it's really nothing not even a
negotiable context but people might say
or you shouldn't be thinking about this
because you won't enjoy life when you
won't enjoy life in an unwholesome sense
but you certainly appreciate it in a
wholesome sense as a possibility of
developing wisdom they will then free
you from death as a possibility for
doing good and maybe showing others who
want to hear so there is still plenty
you can do in this life within the
context of death there won't be as
futile as simply distracting yourself
from the obvious truth and if you close
yourself it will be out of fear so then
okay you might not be able to take it
all in at once which is fine
but you should sell them you know
developer view that you shouldn't be
taking it at all because it's making you
scared no you need to be developing than
yourself in regards to that which scares
you so whereby you won't run away from
that which frightens you
and that's how you get to understand it
and the Buddha says that amongst you
think I could die today a snake could
bite me fall down the elements might
change destroy me my body repeat
whatever it is accident and he thinks
she doesn't go mindlessly through the
motions of snake might bite me I might
fall my heart might stop no he thinks
these things to really look the context
of I am susceptible to die at any given
moment having established a context he
doesn't need to keep thinking about it
because now whatever he does already
maintains the context because that
already is implying yeah I can enter
then give a moment cuz you're somebody's
there's poisonous snakes hmm I could
kill you you don't have to repeat you
say yourself exact thanks the snakes
through the field is not loaded you know
that's what I mean my phone is properly
done it's on the level of knowledge you
know means the thing is there present
the context is there present because you
know it and that's why mindfulness in
memory recollecting it goes hand in hand
because it's not a mechanical focusing
technique that you will be doing on
account of different meditation objects
really developing the knowledge of the
context so there are snakes in the field
you don't go around snakes in the field
snakes in the field whenever you step in
the field that's the context of the
field even if you don't actively think
about it you stick whenever a little
grass moves and touches you and you know
that from experience moves and touches
your ankle you are there in
instantaneously no because the context
is there because it's fully understood
and became part of being in the field
walking in the wilderness you don't
think about it cuz it's there now it's
became part of the significance of the
thing that you're experiencing but that
cannot be done mindlessly becomes part
of the significance when you understood
it as part of significance that's how
you want that's women watchfulness like
you don't forget about it I think even
as a child is similar
example it was like a mother there has
to go into the work outside and leaves
the baby inside so she's out there only
for the amount of time minimum and she
has to finish the work
she doesn't linger she doesn't forget
about her baby she doesn't she doesn't
distract herself from it
means whatever she's doing the back of
her mind still maintains the importance
of a certain context and we choose it
she's done she goes back to it and
that's like the development of mind the
development of mindfulness the
importance of their watchfulness if she
doesn't go down the street leave the kid
alone or get drunk maybe some dude well
yeah I suppose if she cares if she is
concerned about the child she wouldn't
be doing so why would I then be breaking
the precepts why would I then be
careless when I might die within ten
seconds my heart might stop I probably
won't yeah but you might that's more
than enough for that right concern right
type of concern see like you know the
like the Noble Eightfold Path the right
view right intention and so on you could
say that the entire Noble Eightfold Path
is predicated on developing a right
concerned being concerned rightly
becoming aware of that existential
anxiety of dread whatever gonna call it
but you could say it's a right concern
it comes to right responsibility and
then the right view will come out of it
and that's what Buddha meant is what we
said I'm teaching suffering and freedom
from suffering first means you need to
know how to start suffering properly the
right concern the right displeasure yeah
the nature of oh : this is not a choice
this is not negotiable either this
concerns you yeah only means yaki cannot
be compared to other concerns to other
people not it's just my and my only and
this is the only thing worth dealing
with the only thing you can't deal with
truly so developing the right concerned
develop the right to know belief or path
so the mindfulness of death thought the
practice of death again to sit quietly
and think about what you could even
think about your beating heart or your
breathing lungs
I don't negate nothing there's nothing
to negate just be aware that like I am
reading now but I might not be able to
let's think that's the practice of
trying to think about the different ways
that you could die yeah but that's only
only can be indirect like see that's the
thing people people only regard things
that they can think about actually
directly in front of me and something
that I developed no you want to be
discerning the context of what's in
front of you and if you keep making that
context is that in front of you means
the context of that is not in front of
it as in there is something peripheral
to to whatever it's in front of you and
that's what you want to discern like
what we spoke in the doctor if roll
awareness so when you're thinking about
death you come you just visualizing how
you're dying because that's not what
death is for you at a time that's a
particular exemplification of that
possibility but you're not understanding
the certainty of it cuz certainty of
death of the possibility of death is on
the level of the context could you think
will be good do you think whatever
situation how is it possible for me to
die we used a possibility density possible
we used a possibility density possible
you might have to start like that yes
yes and then you'd get a sense of
concern is it and then you recognize
that it's that concern that needs to be
developed must not be distracted from us not be
must not be distracted from us not be
covered up must not be ignored
must not be trying to get rid of it
either oh this is anxiety and concern I
must get rid of it I must get rid of it
establishing the concern the context of
death and then allowing it to endure
because through allowing you to do you
don't need to then worry about whatever
it is in front you because it's going to
be kept in check by the fundamental
concern of liability to death which is
already of concern based on dispassion
contemplation whatever you doing trying
to see that possibility of death I could
I'm sitting now my head yeah yeah okay
you know I understand what you're saying
but the point I'm making is that you can
do that only initially before it becomes
that mechanical just visualizations of
how you might die and you lose the
connection with it that's why you can't
just be focusing on what you gonna think
you have to focus on that emotional
background of being liable to death in
which case you don't need to think
particularly I will die because my heart
will stop our full of the chair you just
need to think I will die I could die and
you already feel it
so it's about picking up the sign
picking up the sign exactly the theme
the context the peripheral off the
actual possibilities of death where's
the flavor exactly and that's gonna be
that kind of initially unpleasant
concern afterwards the displeasure of
that concern disappears because it's
inconceivable to be otherwise so you
might have apprehension and so on but
none of them would be fear and dread and
pain at the prospect of death why cuz
you're not as intoxicated with life as
you were before and you were naughty dog
security because you stopped maintaining
the intoxication and that intoxication
is maintained through ignoring their
concern about the life and it's liable
to death so yes if you want to do
meditation on death think about like
your beating heart I mean you could hear
it you could feel it beating but can you
have any intentional say you realize no
so if this thing stops in this in the
same sense like a branch falls
cop gets knocked over the heart stops
you realize the heart is on the level of
these random things in the world that
can just change because the elements
because of the wind because of the other
whatever but if that does happen my life
is over
so my life entirely my sense of mastery
my sense of control depends on something
s-see his cup be knocked over evolve just pump
his cup be knocked over evolve just pump
just stop stop
ceasing to pump or getting blocked does
the pump get blocked for 10 seconds
might be enough to kill me and you that
is inconceivable to have saying that but
obviously the first reaction to that is
just this overwhelming concern because
of that people feel fully justified I
must not think about this but once you
can use to it that concern cannot
overwhelm you and then literally you
have to all you have to do is just
remember it and you are fully back in
the back in the proper practice of that
recollection of death not through like
randomly visualizing possibilities of
digest my body is a fundamental sort of
basis for my whole life my own
intentions my past my food for
everything yet it's the basis that is
fully accidental and liable to elements
and I cannot even conceive having any
remote input into that domain or that
environment and that makes you feel like
well that prevents you from
appropriating your own life you don't
intention your own sense of control
that's why if you're not overwhelmed by
fear and anxiety and you persevere
through it and you fully maintain this
context this passion is the automatic
result orangy die before you die
as you Hodgins said same same that can
if you use that to revoke concern for
your own life and death as a context
emotional context do you realize I
better deal with this while I can then
it's fine but if you only use it for
some sort of like a you know at arm's
length so to speak not really allow it
to come in because it's gonna overwhelm
you and just try to you know observe and
learn through observation
that's not death that you're learning
about you're learning about the external
manifestation of someone else's death
but unless you allow it to remind you to
reconnect you with your own certain
death impending death
there's no real benefit to it and that's
exactly how people can be dealing with
death on a daily basis and still remain
fully inauthentic
full cover-up of their own death passion
about life like like you think I'm
working morgue or whatever and you might
hit you initially and then you just
cover it up and now it's just cadavers
baby you don't even see that as a
representation of the life that you are
taking it so that's that's what I mean
it takes that you must stop keeping it
in an arm's length but if you don't know
how to deal with it not keeping it at
arm's length it's gonna overwhelm you
that's why it's not optional for people
who don't know how to deal with it to
keep it at arm's length that's the only
mean of self-preservation that they know
and that's why it's gonna be very
frightening and scary but even that gets
taken away when they're actually dying
as that King became aware when to put
explain this to him and that's what
that's why they'll be those people who
would understand what the Buddha's
teaching would freak out and then all
they will kill us and it will said yeah
for any mind that hasn't been sort of
restrained that still venues de pasión
they still values life they still values
are this is mine and I am these truths
will be like frightening terrifying
overwhelming fall on the ground be the
breasts pull their hair full despair
because they realize this is inescapable
the only way to escape it is to stop
appropriating it internally but no sub
appropriating means you have to stop
robbing everything your likes and your
dislikes you have to okay I have to see
them with wisdom and fully understand it
in it in the beginning of that Souter
that I'll read out wait in the beginning
of this talk sir hmm
part I didn't read what's the beginning
I read now cuz it kind of it might make
it okay girlfriend says the rain
saturates things that are covered up it
doesn't saturate things that are open
hmm therefore you should open up a
covered thing so the rain will not
saturate it the world is beaten down by
death and so on and surrounded by old
age first of it so now what you're
saying like okay sounds strange the rain
saturates things that are covered they
even get a chance to dry yeah okay
saturate yeah so you will get you will
get affected by the rain as in you're
gonna get affected by death or even by
anything unpleasant for as long as
you're covering things up from yourself
basically that I mean like all these
truths are they're obvious in a way but
you need to make the effort of undoing
the cover-up for them to be discerned so
it's not like finding the new ways out
it's basically to stop covering up
what's obvious the certainty of death
the certainty of non control the
certainty of change yeah so you realize
these things it's through you ignoring
them i covering them up then you get
liable and you get saturated by the rain
by the grief by despair by sickness
aging and death by everything else that
befalls you it affects you because it's
covered up there and it and it sinks
into it it stays with it
he doesn't go through with it through it
sorry cuz that's the point all these things
cuz that's the point all these things
remain the same for another hunt but
he's not affected by it because he
stopped covering these things up from
him from himself that's what I mean like
when I say self transparent if
something's covered up it's not
transparent you can't see through it so
self transparency that we spoke about
previous talks is developed by
uncovering things up for yourself so
whenever you want to engage in
sensuality or do something out of it
we'll wait remind yourself of the
fundamental context of liability to
death and you realize oh this is not
worth the effort it simply isn't like if
I tell you oh look you know going to
this place get in and it's going to be
the greatest central satisfaction of
every sense you can imagine but there's
also ninety nine pretends to you you're
gonna die no amount of that incitement
would make enter cuz you're just it's
not worth it
cuz now what if I tell you like go in it
go in this place enjoy food and whatever
else but at the end of it within half
now you'll be dead you must die but if
you don't go in you'll live longer you
will go in it because suddenly the whole
enjoyment of sensual distraction and
pleasure is we've placed in an immediate
direct like mirroring of the context
that it's within death if I do this I'm
dead if I don't do it I'm not dead so if
say somebody tells like oh you're
terminal you have three days to live and
tomorrow but today you had plans for
tomorrow hanging out with your friends
some great party care let's get drink
whatever and then later on today you
find out that you have three days to
live would you still have interest to go
around to scale asleep parting with
random people
no you'll be too concerned about is
there anything I can do it before I die
isn't to prevent me from dying is there
anything that they can make difference
to that and you realize that is always
the case as soon as you're born
that's always the context the time is
too short because you can die you will
die at any given period in your life
there's no such thing as too soon
that's why we say Thomas to show don't
be negligent before it's too late so the
context of death immediately D venues
takes value away from anything central
anything based in their will because
yeah there you go you have access to all
of this but death is waiting for you at
the end of it oh I'm not gonna do it
then okay
well it's exactly the same principle
that applies to your life whatever you
do in this life death waits above you
oh okay so then you automatically become
more aware just through discerning that
context nothing else just the abused you
you you remember the appointment the
impending appointment that can be sort
of activated at any time maybe fifty
years maybe in five minutes also does
that make me concern yes why would you
be concerned about like I don't know
something that has no value to you like
some piece of rock if it gets destroyed
somewhere so you have no emotional
connection with it so you couldn't care
less if it gets destroyed so now if
there is concern about you being
destroyed you realize oh so there is
certain emotional connection with this
but is that emotional connection
justified so that's what you start
uncovering your sense of entitlement a
tight entitlement to appropriation of
your own feelings your own intentions
your own sensual pleasures you start
uncovering it you realize no this is not
justified because if these things things
would truly mine if I were truly the
master controller they would not be
liable to death so that's that's the
again the three divine messengers that
they're telling you
what's beneath it but you'd refuse to
admit to yourself they're conveying you
that message but you can only fully
grasp it if you start uncovering it
start drying it up [Music]
so if you want to meditate on it set
like set aside half an hour or whatever
you have without any distractions
think about your liability to death
until you develop that context it slowly
boom not so slightly concerns you and
then just allow it in you if you're
thinking what do I do next
nothing all I do is make sure that this
context remains transparent for this
half an hour that I'm meditating
nothing else so if my thoughts start
coming I led them while I still keep a
cord around that context you fight if I
go away oh I forgot
then you go back to the context and
again just so to let your mind start
going again but you not losing the sight
of the context that's the practice of
mindfulness the results in Samadhi
didn't fees mindfulness because you're
learning how to not forget about the
context even when other things are
happening and that's life so if whatever
is happening in your day-to-day life
then you still have their context at the
back of your mind that is the unshakable
mindfulness where the Buddha meant by it
that is a proper modern on a certain so
whether I'm a meeting in a meeting
taking food or breathing in breathing
out the context remains at the back and
I'm not I have not lost connection with
it
doesn't mean I must have it all the time
in front of me no quite the quad the
opposite means I should be able to allow
it to go as far as you want but I still
won't completely lose the sight of it
and if you think I might not have a
Lhasa is the green diversion delusion in
my mind is the desire for distraction
carelessness sensuality it will anger
yes ah the context I can say I'm rooted
in the context anymore when you rooted
in the context these things cannot arise
amid sensuality amidst irritable things
they can arise because they require
passion and passion and context of death
and mutually exclusive passion requires
that ignoring the fact that it is all
subject to this certain destruction
destruction but if you can't ignore that
anymore means you can't engage in
passion anymore
that's what Buddha meant those people
who are not mindful as
those people who are not aware of their
context there as if dead already they're
fully under that waist of death the only
way to not but taking it not be affected
by it is to fully understand that
context of death so we're being
unmindful you're fully subscribed fully
covered up fully cocooned in that
liability of certain death means you're
as if dead doesn't matter if it's in
five minutes or fifty years you've met
the life the true meaning of life would
be that which is not permeable by death
that which is not subjected to death
there will be the true life oh this is
this is beyond death
but you realize only understanding of
death can be beyond death everything
else is within it so if you have no
understanding of death means your whole
life is already as if dead hence
mindfulness is the path to deathless
peripheral awareness of that context
will take you out of the the
confinements of it through understanding
not like you're going to develop
something outside of it that's
impossible you're going to just lose any passion
you're going to just lose any passion
and appropriation any relationship with
it with everything that's liable to
death which is five aggregates which is
your experience as a whole your life
past future all of it so it's not about
destroying it and not having it arise no
because that's that's something you're
experiencing which means it's another
thing that has arisen for you it's about
removing the emotional connection and
appropriation of it and you will know
you're removing it whereby if you think
about losing your life is there concern
arising is there fear is there worry no
means okay then I'm not holding to
anything even if death comes next second
so if you're practicing meditation of
this you allow it to do for half an hour
40 minutes an hour and then when you're
not meditating you still allow it in the
other one it's there and if it's not
there as much you try and make it back
bring it back even while you have to do
other things because nothing in the
world is an excuse for ignoring the fact
that death is certain it's absolutely no
excuse for that so whatever you engage
with you make sure you keep the keep to
keep a corner of the eye on that
fundamental context and that's what you
are emulating and developing in a more
controlled environment which is what
meditation is but not controlled
environment of a mechanical method but
controlled environment of reflection and
discerning the signs and tokens of how
wide-eyed implication how does it feel
pretty much of being liable to death at
any given moment and you want to see it
on that peripheral level and then okay
I'm aware of it now the mind starts
thinking about things you have to do
about things that happened yesterday but
if that context is there there will be
no passion in regard to it you start
losing the context you re-establish
practice yeah yeah because that's what
mean that's why I was it is coming
before like for people they're so used
to just focusing what's in front of them
and they think if I just learn the art
of focusing regardless of what nature of
things that I'm focusing on is then when
death comes in front to me
I'll be able to you know attend it
rightly but as we described in previous
talks attention is not what's in front
of it the roots of your attention are
from that peripheral which means if you
haven't addressed things on that
peripheral level by the time they're in
front of you it's too late and you can
see that while you're still alive
because truly I mean if you developed
you're focusing so far if there were to
work focusing on the one morning in
front of you you after one session that
focusing you would be completely free
from desire from ill-will from fear from
anything and also but the fact that
you're not means no matter focusing can
help that only understanding they would then
that only understanding they would then
prevent it from affecting you in the
first place because their whole idea of
our practice focusing so when the death
comes I'll know how to deal with it then
all idea is rooted still in the view of
management management is in requiring to
be affected and then learning how to
manage it now you want to approach it
whereby doesn't affect you in the first
place so the only way to reach the
deathless in this life is to really
abandon everything that is subjected to
that death and then you will know that
while you're still alive because if you
wait for death to confirm it to you
means you don't know it means there
won't be a confirmation you want to hear
that's what I don't already knows that
death that has been abandoned and so on
even before he does so if you want to
develop if you want to practice towards
not being affected by the experience of
death when it comes you stop practicing
towards not being affected by any
experience in this life even now so am i
affected by there is an incitement of
sensuality or your will or distraction
or carelessness yes I'm affected by it
that's my work I shouldn't be affected
by it because if I'm not affected by
that I won't be affected by anything
that comes through that that same means
of arising even if it's death itself
but people think I'll just do this
focusing practice and that somehow
magically gonna result in me controlling
yes yes when death comes out well you
know I'll be in charge I'm like are you
in charge now can you say no to yourself
when sensuality presents itself how many
people can answer yes to that question
like I'm not even affected in the first
place let alone I have to manage my
restraint no I'm not affected in the
first place yet here you are expecting
to magically be able to deal with death
simply on account of some mechanical
nostril watching practice the only way
you won't be affected by death is if the
life itself stops affecting you so how
do practice not being affected by life
well you can only do so while you're
still alive you can only do so by
designing what being affected is by
admitting it yourself by uncovering it
by understanding it once you know what
it is you have a sense as well as to
what you have to do in order to not be
affected by it
what life is yeah
the experiences you have in your life
what context it arises in he's always a
cosmic step always internally there's
over the context which is why people
spend most of time covering it up
because it always reveals you that which
you don't want to see necessarily well
rather it takes time and effort to be
able to get used to seeing it and then
not be suffering on account of it that's
where the life samsara and the whole
sensuality goes with the grain it's
effortless to turn a blind eye it's
effortless to engage with sensuality so
you need to start making the effort to
pull yourself out of it before you'll be
able to appreciate and restraint
solitude non distraction normal will you
won't nature aliy value those things
effort and wisdom
so in the meditation practice allowing
that context
concerning context of death to endure
means allowing a degree of fear to arise
and not don't don't give in to trying to
get rid of it right away but allow it to
be there while then the mind is thinking
other things don't automatically fear
and unpleasant I must get rid of this
whatever I do must get rid of this
anxiety on the kind of context of death
why you don't have to get it it doesn't
affect you do anything you don't what
uses to do things on account of it
serial as I can choose not to do
anything on a kind of it I can just
allow it to be there for as long as he
wants to be that's how you automatically
strengthen your mind
that's how he automatically uncovered
anything you've been covering up you
just is gonna take time because you
invested lots of time in covering it up
so the context of death is enduring
you're seated in your room in your Cote
whatever a layperson a monk not
distracted yeah you don't even have to
watch it watch it just don't rush into
overly defining it necessarily it's
gonna become rooted in trying to get rid
of that unpleasant aspect of it just
allow it to endure and sometimes that
endurance will be clearer as in it's
going to be more present sometimes it
will be less but you still recognize it
to a degree it still there so then you
know if there is nothing else going on
because it shouldn't be you're not
protected meditation environment no
distractions as I said let it in do and
then you have a thought of oh after this
summers do this this this and that now
you look at you see that thought against
that backdrop of the context of death as
in things that you must do your duties
are now seen against the context of
death oh you have a memory of something
that happened in the past the bothers
you but now against the context of death
that memory has a reason
and that's already you are not as
bothered as much because you got a
bigger picture now you're not sucked
into what bothers you because you stop
trying to get rid of the unpleasant and
now you have the ultimate unpleasant the
prospect of death any other moving fear
an unpleasant won't be unpleasant so if
those thoughts present themselves you
let him present himself you don't try to
get rid of it you don't try to
overanalyze it overthink it you just
make sure don't forget about a context
of that certain death that I'm concerned
about right now in my meditation while I
let my mind think what he wants to think
and the point will come if you keep
doing it whereby the context will be
movable imperturbable in regard to
whatever your mind thinks
and you will recognize also that the
only way to perturb it is to
intentionally choose to do so by saying
yes to sensuality carelessly saying yes
we will carelessly saying yes to
distraction carelessly no I think about
that later that's already a careless
choice because you're not thinking about
that context that's the point I'm making
you're not I'm thinking about him dead
I'm gonna be dead I'm gonna be dead no
it's a dead enduring on its own you're
actually thinking about your duties or
things that bother your things that you
like that's what you're thinking
but now on the basis of the context that
you discerned
so then context is their peripheral as a
container of all these things that you
do which means they will be less than
the less ground the longer their context
induce less and less basis for passion
towards these particular things will be
and that is effortless as well because
you're not thinking about it what you
need to do is abstain from intentionally
covering it up and abstaining is
effortless it doesn't require you to do
something just requires you to not do
something so that's what meditation is
whatever your object of it might be
developing the same principle peripheral
enduring context it becomes
imperturbable as the Buddha
scribe in Samadhi in regard to things
that are inferior to it things didn't
actually present in themselves let me
say this tablished is his mind in the
the divine abiding of the John and
whether he sits walks buting and Stephie
concedes his mind is divined in that
state because all these things are
inferior to his establishment establish
your mind in the context of death
certain death
absolutely no not even a grain of
opportunity for passion to arise if that
context fully saturate your mind and
that's effortless because the context
isn't there on its own that's what
things are generally subjected it's a
fact it's a factual context the only
reason it's not saturating anything is
because you're covering it up you
covered it up and you keep maintaining
they're covering up through engaging
with with unwholesome sensuality or will
and so on
no no that's that that's the whole point
in the same sense you don't create the
Dhamma even the Buddha said is just an
ancient path that it was covered he
uncovered it he didn't create anything
he said discernment of these factual
universe or truth so that's what
meditation should be revolving around
doesn't matter if you did for fifteen
minutes or for five hours
establishing mind upon the greater
context that there is infertile basis
for any passion any ill-will they cannot
exist on that context and then you let
the context and your until your mind
gets established in it and you know your
mind is established in it when you
cannot be passionate you cannot be
affected by the reason feeling Pleasant
a pleasant or neutral and then you also
know what when when when you're about to
do something if it's gonna make you
firmly more firmly established in that
context so it's gonna take you away from
it the choice becomes much clearer oh
this is a wholesome this is wholesome
unwholesome mints takes you away from
the wholesome context also means keeps
you within the wholesome context on the
basis within that domain doesn't
contradict it doesn't abolish it doesn't
drag you down from it
that's why like David up in the suitors
once he study engaging in unwholesome
act he was unable to establish his mind
in jhanas he wasn't some magical energy
that got trapped or evaporated no it's
just I'm also contradicts the domain of
it if you choose to engage in it you
choose to then forsake this the greater
context and the only way to develop
greater context is to keep discerning it
keep thinking about it
keep trying to establish it allowing it
to endure now trying to get rid of it if
it's unpleasant
that's why you can't crepe for it either
you can't crave for Janice you can't
crave for the imperturbable wholesome
Samadhi because craving is always towards the
because craving is always towards the
actual feeling in regard to the actual
thing that's what you crave for but this
is the context of it in our mind is
establishing that which means your mind
then became unreachable by any craving
hence no room for anything that's based
on their crazy sensuality ill-will
delusion and distraction so if people
wonder how do I make this context endure
you don't do it you can all its enduring
I'm making it endure because it's like
you still trying to make it actually in
front of you so you make it endure but
stop trying to make it endure you make
it in you by thinking about it but by
not interfering about it either so in
the same sense how do you like as we
gave the example of the appointment
life-changing appointment you have you
don't need to make it endure it's
already there all you need to do is stop
distracting yourself from it
you can't cancel them no well you can't
cancel this appointment so okay the
recognition of that it's already a form
of endurance even if I don't necessarily
feel fully concerned about it still I am
aware the context of whatever I do it's
gonna end already subjected that Kiki
can end even before I before I realize
it will end my beating heart right now
can stop after that allowed that thought
wind you don't overthink it don't don't
don't give in to fear of it just allow
it in you that this allowed it thought
in Europe and then see other things that
appear in your mind against enduring of
that thought you're not looking for a
specific answer oh this is what it is or
this is how it will be you're looking
for the like evoking of the context of
being liable to death that's how you
create that connection so while I'm
sitting here breathing secluded from
unwholesome secluded from distraction
what if this beating muscle in my chest
were to stop don't answer it don't
provide an excuse for an explanation
just allow that question to sink in what
if it were to stop and in mind well this
is this all that is secondary still
allowed just a question to endure then
the thought comes he will stop allow
that to do then your timer rings your
meditation finished okay fine but you
realize that context still hasn't
changed okay you go and do your duty now and you
okay you go and do your duty now and you
still have that context enduring and you
will forget it only when you're engaging
and also
last the version of delusion so that's
why yes you need to meditate in this
manner as much as you can until that
context becomes imperturbable but you
could also see you need like a basis of
sense restraint physical restraint as as
a guardian whereby your context is lost
but your bodily behavior speech behavior
even your mental behavior doesn't take
you as far back into the unwholesome so
you won't have to undo it as much and
the virtue comes first it's necessary so
the context is enduring now you still
haven't forgotten that your beating
heart might stop that you're
fundamentally liable to death you have a
degree of concern what do I do now well
you include the thought of what do I do
now against that context and you realize
you don't do anything you don't need to
do anything is the context still there
yes
whatever were to happen to me would it
be against the backdrop of their context
yes whatever I want to do with my life
choose immediately or for the future is
this context changeable no so are my
engagements with life or with people are
they worthy against this context in this
new light of the new context is it
worthy being like you know doing this or
doing that having come here being so
emotional disturbed you know kind of not
getting what I want
really you can't even think if you're in
that context being affected by things
such as sensuality and so on if you're
truly in that context being affected by
those things becomes inconceivable like
even at that very time you're sure you
can forget about the context and then be
affected by it but when you're in the
context it is truly the terrible so you
need to do is find ways of maintaining
the context regardless whether you're
sitting in a protective meditation
environment or not
hence seated walking lying down
extending his arms and eating urinating
defecating whatever we do you maintain
the context day-night to the extent
necessary for obliterating all any
ground for any passion to manifest again
passion not things that you're
passionate the world and that's that's
the meditation object of death